Guide to the Harry Tarzian Photograph Collection 1976-2003 (Bulk 2000-2001) PR 255
New-York Historical Society
Harry Tarzian Photograph Collection
1976-2003 (Bulk 2000-2001)
New-York Historical Society
PR 255
1 Linear feet (1 box)
The collection contains 40 photographs of the World Trade Center and World Trade Center site, taken by Harry Tarzian.
Provenance
Gift of Harry Tarzian, 2006.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Harry Tarzian is an amateur photographer who has lived in Brooklyn, Maryland, and New Jersey.
Scope and Content Note
The Harry Tarzian Photograph Collection spans the period from 1976 to 2003 and contains 40 photographs of the World Trade Center in New York. Nineteen of the photographs are silver gelatin prints. The remaining 21 are inkjet prints made from scanned negatives. They were printed on an Epson Inkjet Printer in 2006.
The photographs of the towers were taken from the New Jersey waterfront, the Brooklyn waterfront, and the Brooklyn Bridge. Others show the towers more close up; several series of images were taken on the vast plaza that surrounded the Trade Center. There are several night views, but most images are daytime views. The earliest photograph was taken on July 4, 1976, during the Bicentennial celebration. A photograph of the plaza from 2000 shows large three-dimensional letters that spell out "Peace on Earth." Several photographs were taken inside the Trade Center. Two of these highlight the large windows in the lobby areas. One photograph shows the shopping mall and entrance to the Path train below the towers. Another shows a newsstand in the New York City subway E train World Trade Center station.
Tarzian was living on a houseboat that was docked in Jersey City when the terrorist attack of September 11, 2001 occurred. Nine photographs show the World Trade Center both after the first tower had been hit by an airplane, after the second tower had been hit, and as the towers collapsed.
One photograph dated 2004 revisits the site of the newsstand in the subway; it has been closed. An undated photograph shows St. Nicholas Greek Orthodox Church, which was demolished when the Trade Center collapsed.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged chronologically. The number of photographs for each year is in parentheses.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other photographs of the World Trade Center can be found in the World Trade Center Photograph Collection (PR 169), the Geographic File (PR 020), and the Thomas Airviews (PR 106).
Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Photographic prints.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Pictorial works.; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.: 1970-2001) -- Pictorial works.; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.: 1970-2001) -- History -- Pictorial works.
- unspecified
  - 1976 (1), 1976 Jul. 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1980, Exteriors (4) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1980, Interiors (2) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1992 (2) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1998 (4) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2000 (11) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - 2001 (5) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - September 11, 2001 (9), 2001 Sep. 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 2003, shuttered newstand (1) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Undated (before September, 2001), ca. 1980-2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)